# **ANDREW LEACH**

Edmonton, AB

+1 780-217-2453

@andrew\_leach

leach.andrew@gmail.com

leach-econ

leachandrew aleach.ca

aleach.ca/charts

## Economist. Data Scientist. Policy Analyst. Academic leader.

I am an energy and environmental economist and Professor at the University of Alberta, where I direct the CABREE research centre and an interdisciplinary electricity research group. My research spans energy and environmental economics with a focus on climate change policies and the law. I have advised federal and provincial governments and provided policy analysis to public- and private-sector clients. I am also an avid data scientist, exploring ways to summarize and visualize energy and economic indicators. I am a prolific writer, with over 200 bylines in major Canadian outlets.

### **EXPERIENCE**

2006 - present Alberta School of Business, University of Alberta

> Professor (2022-present), Associate Professor (2011-2022), and Assistant Professor (2006-2011) Faculty member in the Natural Resources, Energy and Environment (NREE) group, Academic Director

> of CABREE Research Centre (2014-2022), and Future Energy Systems grant holder (2016-2023).

2020 - present Faculty of Law, University of Alberta

**Sessional Instructor** 

Developed and delivered a course on environmental law and policy.

**Economics and Policy Consultant,** 2006 - present

> Environmental policy development and evaluation. Policy advisor to federal and provincial governments. Strategic advisor to corporate boards. Expert witness for energy regulatory proceedings.

2003 - 2006 **HEC Montréal, Institute of Applied Economics** 

Assistant Professor/Professeur Adjoint

#### **EDUCATION**

2019 - 2020 LLM (Constitutional Law), University of Alberta

Thesis examined the constitutional anchors for climate change policies under the POGG, Trade and

Commerce, and Criminal Law powers of the federal government.

1999 - 2003 Ph.D. (Economics). Queen's University

> Thesis focussed on applying numerical methods to examine the economics of climate change policy, including distributional issues and the impacts of uncertainty and learning on optimal policy.

MA (Economics), University of Guelph 1998 - 1999

Focus on environmental, resource, and labour economics.

1994 - 1998 B.Sc. (Environmental Science), University of Guelph

Major: Environmental Economics and Policy.

#### **WORK PRODUCT**

**Publications Academic Publications** aleach.ca/publications

An on-line archive of my academic publications.

Data Data and visualization project archive aleach.ca/projects

Visualization A public archive of data aggregation, collection and visualization tools.

Opinion **Opinion Archive** aleach.ca/opinion

An archive of my public writing, Parliamentary Committee testimony and more.

**LANGUAGES** 

English - native I am an avid cyclist, occasional runner, French - proficient

**HOBBIES** 

downhill and cross-country skier, hockey player, and hobbyist woodworker.

**NON PROFIT** 

Board of Directors, REACH Edmonton and Edmonton Juventus Cycling Club. Past Board Member, River Valley Alliance and Economic Society of Northern Alberta.